Abraham: Cyber security frameworks
are a system of standards, guidelines
for best practice to manage and
mitigate cybersecurity risks.
Nicole: There are many different
types of frameworks according to the
specific areas that they need to cover.
Following an appropriate cyber security
framework will help to manage an
organisations risk, as long as it
takes into consideration specific
needs and priorities of the different
types of businesses and organisations.
Abraham: There are three
broad types of cyber security
frameworks these consists of
• Control frameworks- these are
often used by those who are new
to cyber security, these offer a
basic set of controls to follow.
• Program frameworks -these assess the
overall state of a security program
and help to build and analyse a system
conducting industry comparisons.
• Risk frameworks- these focus on
risk and prioritise security.
Nicole: Defining and communicating
an organisation’s risk regime is
key to their overall cyber security.
The NCSC recommends implementing
10 key steps to help to protect
a business from cyber attack.
Let’s have a look at what is involved.
Abraham: Step 1 is setting
up a risk management regime.
This should be embedded
across an organization and
supported by senior management.
This can involve conducting an
inventory of all resources and risks.
Nicole: Step 2 secure configuration
of all systems should be ensured and
maintained by creating an inventory
and defining a baseline build model.
Also developing a strategy to
remove or disable unnecessary
functionality from any systems.
Abraham: Step 3 Network security.
Networks should be protected from
attack by making sure all connections
in the network are defended for
example by firewalls to filter out
any unauthorized access, including all
cloud services and remote working sites.
Nicole: Step 4 Managing user privileges.
Effective management processes
should limit user privileges, as
unnecessary system privileges can
give rise to potential misuse.
Sensitive information should only be
accessible for those who need to use it.
Abraham: Step 5 User
education and awareness.
Policies should be in place to provide
acceptable and secure use of systems only.
Staff training should make cyber security
a priority to maintain awareness of risks.
Nicole: Step 6 Incident management.
Effective incident management services
will help to maintain resilience and help
potentially reduce any impact to both
the business and stakeholder confidence.
Reporting any criminal activity to
law enforcement is also important.
Abraham: Step 7 Malware protection.
Developing an appropriate antimalware
policy can help to make staff aware
of how malware can infiltrate a
system via phishing scams etc.
Nicole: Step 8 Monitoring.
Establishing a monitoring strategy,
can help to detect attempted attacks
by constantly monitoring all systems
and networks and analyzing logs.
Abraham: Step 9 Removable Media Controls.
Organisations should create a
policy to control all access to
removable media and limit its use.
All media should be scanned for
malware before it enters the system.
Nicole: Step 10 Mobile and Home
working can expose new risks.
It is important to have remote working
policies and train all staff on the use
of remote access and portable systems.
Also making sure all devices have a
baseline security system, can help
to secure systems as can protecting
data in transit and at rest.
Now let’s look at the CIS framework.
The Center for Internet Security [CIS]
has developed a 20-point action plan
that helps organisations to develop
a cyber security framework to prevent
the most common types of attack.
Abraham: This is broken
down into 3 catagories.
1, Identifying the security environment
using basic controls which covers:
Performing an inventory, documenting
all software assets, checking for
software or hardware that may have
been introduced without permission or
knowledge, checking user permissions,
updating passwords and implementing
audit logs and other management systems.
Nicole: 2, Protecting assets with
foundational controls which covers:
Checking email and browsers are
up to date and protected, malware
and virus protection, preventing
unauthorized connections, backup
and recovery plans, secure network
configurations, boundary defences,
data protection measures, additional
access controls, wireless access
controls, account monitoring controls.
Abraham: 3, Developing a security
culture using organizational
controls which covers:
Implementing security awareness
training, managing the security
lifecycle, developing incident response
procedures, performing penetration tests.
As we have discussed there are many
different types of cyber security
frameworks, but they all do a similar
job of helping organisations to design
their own cyber security system.
Nicole: It is the cyber security
professional’s role to evaluate
and apply the appropriate
framework for their organization.
Focusing on the business needs
and what elements are the most
important according to the type
of traffic an organization has.
Control frameworks work well for
those organisations that are new
to managing a security program
identifying the current state and
prioritizing future developments.
Abraham: Program frameworks like the
National Institute of Standards and
Technology [NIST] can help build a mature
program and improve information security.
Risk frameworks includes more controls
and management across a wider range
of business operations taking a
systematic approach to risk management.